Register of the Frederick Russell Burnham Papers, 1879-1979
Hoover Institution Archives
Frederick Russell Burnham Papers,
1879-1979
78082
Burnham, Frederick Russell, 1861-
7 manuscript boxes, 24 envelopes, 1 album box (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, clippings, other printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to the Matabele Wars of 1893 and 1896 in Rhodesia, the Boer War, exploration expeditions in Africa, and gold mining in Alaska duing the Klondike gold rush.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Great Britain. Army.; Klondike gold fields.; Matabele War, 1893.; Matabele War, 1896.; South African War, 1899-1902.; Africa.; Africa--Discovery and exploration.; Alaska.; Great Britain.; Rhodesia.; South Africa.; United States.; Zimbabwe.
Introduction
Born in the USA Burnham was brought up in California. He received a limited formal education but in the course of his early working life in the Western USA he acquired a knowledge of mining, particularly gold mining. From 1893 to 1897 he was in present-day Zimbabwe and Zambia. It was he who led the Northern Territories (BSA) Exploration Co. expedition which established for the outside world that major copper deposits existed in Central Africa.
In 1897 Burnham left Africa to take up gold mining in Alaska and the Klondike but in 1900 he returned to become the chief scout of the British forces engaged in the Boer War. In 1901, having been wounded, he left South Africa for London. There he was employed by the Wa Syndicate. For the Wa Syndicate he led an expedition through Ghana and Upper Volta which was concerned both with mineral occurrences and the possibility of improving the navigability of major rivers. He also served the Wa Syndicate as their London office manager.
From 1902 to 1904 Burnham was employed by the East Africa Syndicate. For them he led a mineral prospecting expedition which travelled extensively in the area around Lake Rudolph. Thereafter he was engaged in projects in the Americas for, or in cojunction with, John Hays Hammond, the mining magnate. During the 1920s and 1930s Burnham was engaged in the management of the Dominguez oilfield in California.
The papers of Frederick Burnham are not all in one place. One stray item is in the National Archives of Zimbabwe 1. The remainder are split between Yale University Library 2 and the Hoover Institution's Archives. The papers at Yale University were gifted by Major Burnham's widow in 1951. Those at the Hoover Institution she gifted in 1978. Whilst most of those gifted to Yale are subject to a closure which renders them inaccessible until the year 2000 3, those at the Hoover Institution are open. The latter contain a substantial number of transcripts, that is to say copies laboriously made by hand from diaries, letters, etc. the originals of which are (in most cases, at least) now at Yale. One file of correspondence at the Hoover Institution Archives contains both transcripts and the originals from which they were copied 4: the transcripts are highly accurate. That the same is true of the other transcripts at the Hoover Institution can not, however, be guaranteed. Whilst some papers are in both repositories (the originals at Yale and the transcipts at the Hoover Institution) this is by no means the whole picture. Some papers at Yale (on mines in Chile and China, for instance) are not duplicated in the papers at the Hoover Institution. Vice versa, some materials at the Hoover Institution are not duplicates of papers at Yale.
1. Baxter, T.W. and Burke, E.E. Guide to the Historical Manuscripts in the National Archives of Rhodesia, 1970, p.67.
2. Yale University Library, Manuscripts and Archives, New Haven, Connecticut 06520.
3. A collection of writings about Burnham and working papers for his two books Scouting on Two Continents (1928) and Taking Chances (1944) are open for research use.
4. Folder Lummis, Charles F., Folder 10 in Box 3.
Biographical Note
1861, May 11 Born, Tivoli, Minnesota
1870 Family moved to Los Angeles
1878-1882 Cowboy, hunter, prospector and scout in Arizona and Texas
1884 Marriage to Blanche Blick
1893 Trooper in BSA Police, Rhodesia [Zimbabwe]
1895 Prospecting in North West Rhodesia [Western Zambia]
1896-1897 Scout for British forces in Matabele [Ndebele] wars
1897-1900 Gold mining in Alaska and Klondike
1900-1901 Chief Scout of British forces in Boer War
1901 Awarded Distinguished Service Order
1901-1902 Working for Wa Syndicate in Gold Coast [Ghana] and London
1902-1904 Working for East Africa Syndicate. Led mineral prospecting expedition to Lake Rudolph
[1908-?] Engaged in irrigation project in Yacqui River Delta, Mexico
1912-[?] Director of Yacqui Delta Land and Water Co.
[1917-1918] Manager of manganese and tungsten survey of Western USA
[?] Manager of Burnham Exploration Co. [later Dominguez Oil Fields Co.]
1923 Burnham Exploration Co. and Union Oil Co. agreed to develop Dominguez Oilfield on a 50:50 basis
1928 Author, Scouting on Two Continents
[?] Director of Union Oil Co.
1939 Death of Mrs Blanche Burnham
1943 Marriage to Ilo K. Willits [or Ferrce]
1944 Author, Taking Chances
1947 Died, California
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1890-1948. (Box 1-2)
  Biographical data and writings, a family tree, correspondence, clippings and publications.
  - General
    - Correspondence, notes and clippings re Burnham and Russell family history. Photographic materials were removed from this file and placed in envelope J, 78082-10.A-V. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Notes and clippings re Frederick R. Burnham (Folder 3)
  - Publications and Eulogies
    - Britt, Albert, The Boy's Own Book of Adventurers, 1923 (Folder 4)
    - Davis, Richard Harding, Real Soldiers of Fortune, 1907. See also correspondence with Davis (Box 2 Folder 10 below) (Folder 5)
    - Goodland, Colonel H.T., Hail and Farewell, 1948 (Folder 6)
    - Lang, Andrew, The Red True Story Book, 1921 (Folder 7)
    - Russell, Charles Edward, A Pioneer Editor in Early Iowa, 1941 (Folder 8)
    - West, James E. and Lamb, Peter O., He Who Sees in the Dark, 1932 (Folder 9)
    - West, James E. (Compiler), The Boy Scout's Book of True Adventure, 1931 (Folder 10)
    - S.J. Clarke Publishing Co., California of the South, a History, vol. 41933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1890-1963. (Box 2-3)
  Correspondence and transcripts of correspondence of Frederick R. and Ilo K. Burnham, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Baden-Powell, Lord Robert and Lady Olave, 1900-1953. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Subjects include: Boer War; Boy Scouts; British army training; Yacqui Valley, Mexico
  - Bent, Arthur, 1899-1929. (Folder 3)
    Subjects include: Bardeen Oil Trust; Western USA irrigation and dam schemes
  - Boy Scouts, 1909-1958 (Folder 4)
  - Boy Scouts, Phoenix, Arizona, 1941-52 (Folder 5)
  - Brooke, Jack, 1903-1908. (Folder 6)
    Subjects include: travels around Lake Rudolph, East Africa, 1903; expedition to Tibet, 1905-1908
  - Burnham, Mrs. Blanche B., 1890-1892. Letters to Mrs. Burnham in California from her husband in Colorado and Missouri (Folder 7)
  - Christie-Crawford, Captain Alan, 1932-1950 (Folder 8)
  - City of Bulawayo, Southern Rhodesia (Zimbabwe), 1946-1963. Invitations to formal occasions (Folder 9)
  - Davis, Bob, 1940-1942 (Folder 10)
  - Davis, Richard Harding, 1906. (Folder 11)
    Subjects include chapter on Frederick R. Burnham in Davis's book Real Soldiers of Fortune
  - Dominguez Oil Fields Co., 1944-1946. (Folder 12)
    Subjects include management of Frederick R. Burnham's shareholding
  - Fisher, Sir Godfrey and Lady Geraldine, 1946-1960 (Folder 13)
  - Fry, Verle N., 1942-1944. (Folder 14)
    Subjects include copyright on Burnham's book Taking Chances
  - Gifford, Lord, and members of his family, 1896-1940. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Subjects include wars in Rhodesia (Zimbabwe) and South Africa. Contains agreement between Frederick R. Burnham, Hon. Maurice Gifford and Pearl Ingram and Lord Gifford and F.I. Ricarde-Deaver for the exploitation of a concession in Rhodesia
  - Grant, Madison, 1928-1934. (Folder 2)
    Subjects include Redwoods Preservation League
  - Gross, Theodore, 1942-1947. (Folder 3)
    Subjects include: possible film of Burnham's book Scouting on Two Continents; rifle training for Boy Scouts
  - Haggard, Sir H. Rider, 1922-1924. (Folder 4)
    Subjects include Frederick R. Burnham's activities on behalf of J.H. Hammond in Mexico and the USA
  - Hammond, John Hays, 1905-1936. (Folder 5)
    Subjects include: Burnham Exploration Co.; Colorado River Valley Development; develpment of the gas lift method of oil extraction; Dominguez Oil Field; land dealings; Hammond's campaign to become Secretary for the Interior; Union Oil Co.; Yacqui Delta Land and Water Co., Mexico
  - Henry, Bill, 1943-1947 (Folder 6)
  - Holder, Frederick, 1909-1917. (Folder 7)
    Subjects include: preservation of California's wildlife; public relations aspects of Yacqui Delta developments; publishing propositions
  - Hunter-Weston, General Sir Aylmer, 1911-1937. (Folder 8)
    Subjects include: American and British politics; World War One
  - Kennedy, William P., 1945-1953. (Folder 9)
    Subjects include publication of Burnham's book Taking Chances
  - Lummis, Charles F., 1908-1927. (Folder 10)
    Subjects include Southwest Society (of the) Archaeological Society of America. See also Box 3 Folder 6 below
  - Mackie, W.W., 1916-1945. (Folder 11)
    Subjects include development of irrigation crops
  - Macomber, A.K. and H.J., 1910-1946. (Folder 12)
    Subjects include gift of the Macomber collection of artefacts from Africa and Oceania to Arizona State Museum. Contains report on Black Bear gold mine prepared by Frederick R. Burnham, 1915. See also Box 3 Folder 19 below
  - The Outpost (Regimental Magazine of the British South Africa Police), 1941-1947 (Folder 13)
  - Paddon, Major Cecil, 1945-1953. (Folder 14)
    Subjects include Society of Members of the 1893 Columns, Rhodesia (Zimbabwe)
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1910-1939. (Folder 15)
    Subjects include Republican Party politics
  - Posselt, E. Harry, 1946-1952 (Folder 16)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, and Roosevelt Memorial Association, 1917-1949. (Folder 17)
    Subjects include proposal to form an American volunteer force to fight against Germany, 1917. See also Box 4 Folder 1 below
  - Schleger (Schlegal), Oswald, 1936-1954 (Folder 18)
  - Stauffer, Charles A., 1946-1949. (Folder 19)
    Subjects include Arizona State Museum. See also Box 3 Folder 12 above
  - Wright, Howard (Howell), 1940-1954. (Folder 20)
    Subjects include gift of papers of Frederick R. Burnham to Yale University's Howell Wright Collection of Rhodesiana and South Africana
- CORRESPONDENCE, MISCELLANEOUS, 1893-1964. (Box 4)
  Correspondence and transcripts of correspondence of Frederick R. and Ilo K. Burnham, arranged chronologically.
  - 1893-1927 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Subjects include: Frederick R. Burnham's South California manganese mine interests, 1916-1917; journey on East African coast, 1893; mineral prospecting in the vicinity of Lake Rudolph, East Africa, 1904; proposal to form an American volunteer force to fight against Germany, 1917; Republican Party politics, 1908-1912; Rhodesia (Zimbabwe), 1896-1902; US policy towards Mexico, 1915; Wa Syndicate, Gold Coast (Ghana), 1901. Contains agreement for payment of Frederick R. Burnham as selling agent for Tehama timber lands, 1917.
  - 1930-1964 (Folder 2)
    Subjects include reminiscences of Frederick R. Burnham and of his former colleagues and comrades.
- CORRESPONDENCE OF ILO K. BURNHAM, 1934-58. (Box 4)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Crook, Colonel W.J., and (?), George, 1934-1944. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Subjects include: California Arabian Standard Oil (Corporation?), Bahrien; Rock Island Arsenal, Illinois
  - Knowland, Senator William F., 1950-1958 (Folder 4)
  - Millikan, Robert A., 1948-1952 (Folder 5)
  - Southwest Museum, Los Angeles, 1946-1948. See also Box 3 Folder 6 above (Folder 6)
  - Stiles, John A., 1948-1958 (Folder 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE OF J.E. ELLIOT (Box 4)
  - Burnham, Ilo. K., 1975-1979. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Subjects include gift of Burnham papers to Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1911-1949. (Box 4-5)
  Notes for speeches and drafts and printed copies of books and articles by Frederick R. Burnham, with correspondence and notes, chronological order.
  - Speeches, 1911-1939. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Subjects include: Arizona State Museum's Macomber Collection; Frederick R. Burnham's early life in California and other Western states; game ranching; State Parks. Most speeches delivered to Sunsetters Club, Los Angeles
  - Scouting on Two Continents, 1928
    - Fra Alaska Til Kap (Danish edition) (Folder 10)
    - Manuscript and typescript drafts, including substantial amount of unpublished material (Folder 11)
  - Taking Chances, 1944 (Box 5)
    - Burnham, Frederick R., Taking Chances, Haynes Corporation, 1944, a copy as published (Folder 1)
    - Copies of inscriptions written in presentation copies of Taking Chances. The recipients are named and numbered to 464 (Folder 2-3)
    - Letters of thanks from recipients and requests for copies (Folder 4)
    - Drafts of chapter on Winston Churchill with related papers (Folder 5)
    - Haynes Corporation, printers. Correspondence and invoices (Folder 6)
    - Historical Society of Southern California Quarterly, 1942 March (containing article apparently used by Frederick R. Burnham) (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous writings
    - Rhodes, Cecil. Drafts of an article with related papers, 1902-1944 (Folder 8)
    - Selous, Frederick C. Drafts of an article for the Boone and Crockett Club Annual Report, 1929 (Folder 9)
    - Wholly miscellaneous writings. (Folder 10)
      Subjects include: hanting, mining, prospecting and scouting in the USA and Africa; proposal to form an American volunteer force to fight against Germany; Theodore Roosevelt, 1920s-1940s
- NOTEBOOKS, 1895-1946. (Box 6)
  Notebooks containing transcripts of correspondence, agreements, diaries and reports, arranged by provenance of documents transcribed.
  - Transcripts of agreements, correspondence and reports. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Subjects include: East African Syndicate, 1902-1909; Matabele (Ndebele) War, 1896-1897; Northern Territories (BSA) Exploration Co. 1895-1899; Wa Syndicate, 1901-1902
  - Transcripts of letters sent by Frederick R. Burnham to Northern Territories (BSA) Exploration Co., H. Greene and Lord Gifford re business transactions including land deals, mineral developments and Northern Rhodesian (Zambian) concessions, 1897 (Folder 2)
  - Transcripts of correspondence, orders and reports, 1900-1905. (Folder 3)
    Subjects include: Boer War; East Africa Syndicate
  - Transcripts of correspondence and memoirs, 1917-1946. (Folder 4)
    The memoirs concern Earl Grey, Sir H. Rider Haggard and E.H. Harriman. Subjects of the correspondence include the oil extraction industry in California
  - Transcripts of diaries kept by A. King Macomber, John Blick (?) Gillfillan and (?) Stewart whilst mineral prospecting in Northern Rhodesia (Zambia) for the Northern Territories (BSA) Exploration Co., 1895. Minerals mentioned include copper, gold and salt (Folder 5)
  - Transcripts of diary kept by John Blick whilst on Wa Syndicate expedition in Gold Coast (Ghana), 1901. (Folder 6)
    Subjects include: gold deposits; possibility of improving the navigability of inland waterways. Contains an account of North Eastern Hausaland taken down in writing by John Blick from one of his porters
- SUBJECT FILE, 1899-1936. (Box 6)
  - Alaska and Klondike, 1899-1936. Transcripts of correspondence, working papers for a publication and printed ephemera. Photographic materials were removed from this file and placed in envelope G, 78082-10.A-V. (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
- CLIPPINGS, 1879-1951. (Box 6-7)
  Clippings from African, American and British newspapers, arranged chronologically.
  - 1879-1944 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Subjects include Rhodesia.
  - 1893-1901 (Folder 11)
    Subjects include: Rhodesia; South Africa; West Africa.
  - 1896-1918 (Folder 12)
    Subjects include: Rhodesia; South Africa.
  - 1900-1909 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Subjects include: Boer War; East Africa; Mexico; West Africa.
  - 1910-1919 (Folder 2)
    Subjects include: game ranching; mineral surveying in North America; World War One.
  - 1910-1946 Miscellaneous. (Folder 3)
  - 1920-1929. (Folder 4)
    Subjects include: California State Park Commission; Frederick R. Burnham's travels in Australasia; publication of Scouting on Two Continents; Save the Redwoods League
  - 1930-1939. Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
  - 1931-1935. (Folder 6)
    Subjects include Major G.H. Schoof
  - 1940-1951. (Folder 7)
    Contains obituaries of Frederick R. Burnham
- MEMORABILIA (Memorabilia-cabinet Memorabilia cabinet)
  - 1 Child's sherrif badge, 1905 (Memorabilia-cabinet Memorabilia cabinet)
  - 1 Conker (Horse Chestnut nut)
  - 1 Cut-throat razor
  - 1 Cycle padlock
  - 1 Decorated card with message in (Arabic?)
  - 1 Facsimile of a small stone inscribed with (Egyptian?) hieroglyphs
  - 10 Glass negatives depicting East Africa, 1902-1903
  - 1 Gollywog lapel pin
  - 1 Greek medallion, modern
  - 1 Gunpowder can, small
  - 1 Indigenous worked copper artefact, Central African, late Nineteenth Century
  - 1 Lock of hair, Mrs. William Russell
  - 1 Medallion inscribed Courage, Loyalty, Honor
  - 6 Mineral samples
  - 3 North American Indian pouches
  - 1 Printing block, Frederick R. Burnham
  - 1 Sample book depicting Spanish tiles, 1930s or 1940s
  - 1 Sea horse
  - 1 Sea shell
  - 1 Sheath for a knife
  - 1 Snake skin
  - 1 Southern Rhodesian (Zimbabwean) crown (coin), 1953
  - 1 (Stirrup?)
  - 1 Token issued by J. Lawley, Cape Town, (1900?)
- PHOTOGRAPHS. (Othertype 78082 - 10.A-V Slide Cabinet Memorabilia Cabinet)
  - 164 prints depicting East African scenes, people and mineral occurrences, mostly Nairobi and vicinity of lake Rudolph, 1902-1903 (Folder A)
  - 18 prints depicting Rhodesian (Zimbabwean) scenes, including Great Zimbabwe, undated (Folder B)
  - 23 prints depicting South African and Rhodesian (Zimbabwean) scenes, including commemoration ceremonies for the 1893 pioneer columns in Rhodesia (Zimbabwe)., 1890s-1940s. (Folder C)
  - 7 prints depicting an exhibition of the Howell Wright Collection of Rhodesiana and South Africana in Cleveland public library prior to its presentation to Yale University Library., 1950? (Folder D)
  - 145 prints depicting scenes, people, mineral occurrences and military forces in Golf Coast (Ghana) and Upper Volta, including Kintampo market women and villages destroyed by Samori., 1901 (Folder E)
  - 28 prints depicting miscellaneous African subjects, undated (Folder F)
  - 14 prints depicting houses, street scenes and local scenery in and around Skagway, Alaska, 1899? (Folder G)
  - 3 prints with one related press clipping depicting Tibet and/or Western China, taken by Jack Brooke., 1909? (Folder H)
  - 24 prints and 1 sketch depicting Frederick R. Burnham., 1900s-1940s (Folder I)
  - 20 prints depicting members of the Burnham and Russell families and their automobiles., 1861-1904 (Folder J)
  - 35 prints depicting members of Frederick R. Burnham's family in Alaska, Britain, California and East Africa., 1880s-1940s (Folder K)
  - 15 prints depicting Frederick R. Burnham's early homes in California, 1880s-? (Folder L)
  - 53 prints depicting Frederick R. Burnham's Hollywood homes, including trophies and other memorabilia collected whilst travelling., 1930s-1940s (Folder M)
  - 17 prints depicting Frederick R. Burnham's homes and grave., ?-1940s (Folder N)
  - 39 prints depicting Frederick R. Burnham's personal friends and their homes., 1890s-1940s (Folder O)
  - 10 prints, no common factor, 1870s-1940s, including 1870 lynching in Los Angeles, 190? inscribed stone, Yacqui Valley, Mexico, 1938 Dominguez Oilfield. (Folder P)
  - 61 negatives depicting East Africa, 1902-1903 (Folder Q)
  - 53 negatives depicting West Africa, 1901 (Folder R)
  - 25 negatives depicting Frederick R. Burnham's Hollywood homes, 1930s-1940s (Folder S)
  - 3 negatives depicting a group including W. Glenn Campbell outside Stanford University Faculty Club., 1972 (Folder T)
  - 61 postcards and 1 Christmas card depicting Alaska Rhodesia and other subjects. (Folder U)
  - 31 prints depicting one of Frederick R. Burnham's Hollywood homes., 1940s (Folder mV-mW)
  - 4 prints, no common factor, undated (Folder mX)
  - 9 prints depicting Alaska, 1930s (Folder m*Y)
  - 3 prints and 2 cartoons, no common factor, 1900-1939, including, 1938-1939 Sunset Club Christmas dinner parties, 1939 Kofa Mountain Game Range, Arizona. (Folder m*Z)
  - album containing 20 prints depicting one of Frederick R. Burnham's California Homes, 1930s or 1940s (Folder fAA)
  - 23 slides depicting Frederick R. Burnham, one of his homes and a Boy Scout memorial to him, 1940s-1950s (Folder Slides)
  - 10 glass negatives depicting East Africa, 1902-1903 (Folder Memorabilia Cabinet)